<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>SciRuby</title>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/"/>
  <updated>2011-08-23T14:44:15-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://sciruby.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>SciRuby</name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>Interview with the SciRuby Team</title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/17/interview-with-the-sciruby-team/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-17T21:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/17/interview-with-the-sciruby-team</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We just had an interview published today over at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.floss4science.com/interview-sciruby-team/&quot;&gt;Floss for Science&lt;/a&gt;,
 and we're super excited because it's our very first media coverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to vote it up at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;, that would be outstanding &amp;emdash; or share it however you
 like to share things. Here are the links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/jlh19/interview_sciruby_team/&quot;&gt;/r/programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/jlkur/interview_sciruby_team/&quot;&gt;r/ruby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Already we've had a bunch of new people joining us on IRC (#sciruby on Freenode) and in our
 &lt;a href=&quot;http://groups.google.com/group/sciruby-dev&quot;&gt;Google Group&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks for all your support!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Challenges of Copyrights</title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/15/the-challenges-of-copyrights/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-15T19:56:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/15/the-challenges-of-copyrights</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week, I thought it would be fun to translate some of the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nr.com/&quot;&gt;Numerical Recipes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; algorithms into Ruby,
 specifically those for the Gamma distribution and incomplete gamma function. I got them all working pretty well, and
 they were only a hundred or so lines of code altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a voice in the back of my head said, &quot;Hey, you should ask Bill Press if he wants to be involved.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_H._Press&quot;&gt;Bill Press&lt;/a&gt;, by the way, is a pretty cool astrophysicist who decided he
 wanted to come work here at UT as a computational biologist instead. He also happens to be first author on &lt;em&gt;Numerical
 Recipes&lt;/em&gt;, and a fairly regular attendee at my lab's weekly meetings. Once he had to pause my exam to take a call
 from the White House, which was also pretty awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I emailed Dr. Press to ask him if he'd be interested in helping out with SciRuby, and specifically if he might be
 willing to donate a copy of NR. He was happy to donate a copy and to help out in whatever way he could, he wrote back,
 but the license for NR wouldn't allow us to use the code from the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My stomach sank. I had missed that disclaimer, and I was used to dealing with more-or-less public domain (or at least
 GPLed) Ruby code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The email continued. We should be careful using other libraries, because many of them were illegally derived from
 copyrighted materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several interesting discussions ensued (&lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/108379995018215027591/posts/2AefG8i3nUX&quot;&gt;including this public one&lt;/a&gt;).
 The take-away is that many people don't understand code copyrights (I among them). Consequently, most governments don't
 understand copyrights (and it doesn't help that U.S. Congress isn't exactly full of programmers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some were critical of Press and his coauthors for not simply giving us special permission to use his code, but such a
 gimme would be complicated for NR. If they permitted us to use NR code in SciRuby, that code would then be available to
 anyone else to use under the terms of the GPL. I imagine his publisher would be less than thrilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are some general guidelines for those who want to contribute code to an open-source scientific project,
 particularly SciRuby. Please keep in mind that I am not a lawyer, and take any of this with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If in doubt, check with the author.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do unto others as you would have them do unto you. In other words, honor closed source licenses if you wish your open
source license to be honored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Always cite your sources.&lt;/em&gt; If a copyright owner discovers apparently derivative code without a citation, it's easy
to him or her to assume you plagiarized it directly from his or her work. If it has a citation, someone else gets the
blame, or the copyright owner can determine that the code is only &lt;em&gt;apparently&lt;/em&gt;, but not &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt;, derivative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you write your own code, derived from your own math, document it. Scan your derivation and make it public (send it
to our Google Group, for example).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Any more words of wisdom? Stick them in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>First Post!</title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/15/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-15T19:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/15/first-post</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I thought I'd start by introducing myself. I'm the project director for SciRuby, and I'm a molecular biology doctoral
 student at the University of Texas. I work in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://marcottelab.org/&quot;&gt;Marcotte Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and actually occupy the
 former desk (and lab hostname) of John Prince, another of the SciRuby project leads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to working as a graduate student, I am a blogger and an offline political activist -- specifically, a
 community organizer. While I have contributed code to SciRuby already, and plan to continue, my main role here derives
 from my community organizing experience: &lt;strong&gt;I want &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; to get involved.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that vein, I have written &lt;a href=&quot;http://sciruby.com/blog/2011/08/15/the-challenges-of-copyrights/&quot;&gt;a fascinating (and humble) precautionary tale&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and if do you want to get involved, you can find us in #sciruby (Freenode.net), or you can come check out our
&lt;a href=&quot;http://groups.google.com/group/sciruby-dev&quot;&gt;Google Group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
