<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: linear algebra | SciRuby]]></title>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/categories/linear-algebra/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-25T08:52:04-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://sciruby.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SciRuby]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GSoC 2015: New NMatrix gems for advanced linear algebra features]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2015/08/19/gsoc-2015-nmatrix/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T09:57:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2015/08/19/gsoc-2015-nmatrix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My Google Summer of Code project was working on the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix">NMatrix project</a>, moving
functionality that depends on external libraries from the core <code>nmatrix</code>
gem to optional plugin gems. NMatrix is a Ruby library for linear algebra,
used by many other projects.
In addition to the code that was part of
NMatrix proper, NMatrix previously required the <a href="http://math-atlas.sourceforge.net/">ATLAS library</a>, which
implemented fast versions of common matrix operations like multiplication
and inversion, as well as more advanced operations like eigenvalue
decomposition and Cholesky decomposition.</p>

<p>There were two separate but related motivations for my project. The
first was to simplify the NMatrix installation
process. ATLAS can be difficult to install, so the installation
process for NMatrix was complicated, especially on
OS X, and may have discouraged people from using NMatrix.
The second motivation was that by separating out the ATLAS code from the
main NMatrix code, it would be easier to add new linear algebra backends
which provide similar features. Indeed, I implemented a second backend this
summer.</p>

<p>The end result of my summer's work:</p>

<ul>
<li>The core <code>nmatrix</code> gem does not depend on any external linear matrix
libraries. It provides non-optimized implementations of common matrix
operations.</li>
<li>All code that requires ATLAS has been moved into the new <code>nmatrix-atlas</code>
gem, so that
those who are only interested in the core functionality are not required to
install ATLAS. <code>nmatrix-atlas</code> provides optimized implementations of common matrix
operations, as well as advanced functions not available in <code>nmatrix</code>.
I wrote a blog post describing the setup for <a href="http://wlevine.github.io/2015/06/15/releasing-multiple-gems-with-c-extensions-from-the-same-repository.html">releasing multiple gems from the same repository</a>, which this required.</li>
<li>A new gem <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code>, which provides the same features as
<code>nmatrix-atlas</code>, but instead of depending specifically on the ATLAS
library, requires any generic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LAPACK">LAPACK</a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Linear_Algebra_Subprograms">BLAS</a>
implementation. This should be easier to use for many users as they may
already have LAPACK installed (it comes pre-installed with OS X and is
commonly used in Linux systems), but not ATLAS.</li>
<li>The installation procedure is simplified, especially for those installing
just the <code>nmatrix</code> gem. Compare the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/wiki/Installation">new installation instructions</a>
to the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/wiki/Installation/2ac41c62d35c79468d3d8169be0ccba238c3c921">old ones</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>The one deviation from my original proposal was that I originally intended to remove
all the ATLAS code and release only the <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> plugin, so that we
would only have one interface to the advanced linear algebra functions, but I
decided to keep the ATLAS code, since the <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> code is new and
has not had a chance to be thoroughly tested.</p>

<h3>Usage</h3>

<p>```ruby
require 'nmatrix'</p>

<h1>create a 3-by-3 matrix</h1>

<p>a = NMatrix.new([3,3], [1,2,3, 4,5,6, 7,8,9], dtype: :float64)</p>

<h1>invert it using non-optimized NMatrix-internal implementation</h1>

<p>a.invert!
```</p>

<p>```ruby
require 'nmatrix'
require 'nmatrix/atlas' #or require 'nmatrix/lapacke'</p>

<h1>create a 3-by-3 matrix</h1>

<p>a = NMatrix.new([3,3], [1,2,3, 4,5,6, 7,8,9], dtype: :float64)</p>

<h1>invert it using optimized implementation provided by ATLAS</h1>

<p>a.invert!
```</p>

<p>For advanced functions not provided by the core <code>nmatrix</code> gem, for example
<a href="http://sciruby.com/nmatrix/docs/NMatrix.html#method-i-gesvd"><code>gesvd</code></a>, <code>nmatrix-atlas</code> and <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code>
provide a common interface:</p>

<p><code>ruby
require 'nmatrix'
require 'nmatrix/atlas'
a = NMatrix.new([4,5],[1,0,0,0,2, 0,0,3,0,0, 0,0,0,0,0, 0,4,0,0,0],
dtype: dtype)
u, s, vt = a.gesvd
</code></p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>Identical to the above, except for the require</h1>

<p>require 'nmatrix'
require 'nmatrix/lapacke'
a = NMatrix.new([4,5],[1,0,0,0,2, 0,0,3,0,0, 0,0,0,0,0, 0,4,0,0,0],
dtype: dtype)
u, s, vt = a.gesvd
```</p>

<p>If the developer wants to use an advanced feature, but does not care
whether the user is using <code>nmatrix-atlas</code>
or <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code>, they can <code>require nmatrix/lapack_plugin</code>, which will
require whichever of the two is available, instead of being forced to
choose between the two.</p>

<p>As a fun test of the new gems, I did a very simple benchmark, just
testing how long it took to invert a
1500-by-1500 matrix in place using <code>NMatix#invert!</code>:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>nmatrix</code> (no external libraries): 3.67s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-atlas</code>: 0.96s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> with ATLAS: 0.99s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> with OpenBLAS (multithreading enabled): 0.39s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> with reference implementations of LAPACK and BLAS: 3.72s</li>
</ul>


<p>This is not supposed to be a thorough or realistic benchmark (performance will
depend on your system, on how you built the libraries, and on the exact
functions that you use), but there
are still a few interesting conclusions we can draw from it:</p>

<ul>
<li>Performance is much better using the two highly optimized libraries
(ATLAS and OpenBLAS) than using either the NMatrix
internal implementation or the reference implementation.</li>
<li>When using ATLAS, performance is similar whether using <code>nmatrix-atlas</code>
and <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> (this means we could consider deprecating
the <code>nmatix-atlas</code> gem).</li>
</ul>


<p>Overall, my summer has been productive. I implemented everything that I
proposed and feedback from testers so far has been positive.
I plan to stay involved with NMatrix, especially to follow up on any issues
related to my changes.
Although I won't be a student next summer, I would certainly consider
participating in Google Summer of Code in the future as a mentor.
I'd like to
thank my mentor John Woods and the rest of the SciRuby community for support
and feedback throughout the summer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
