<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: NMatrix | SciRuby]]></title>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/categories/nmatrix/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sciruby.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-02-21T12:51:17+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://sciruby.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SciRuby]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tensors using NumRuby]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2021/02/16/tensors/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-16T21:49:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2021/02/16/tensors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tensor word can have slightly different meaning depending upon the nature of study, like it's defined differently in Physics, slightly different in computer science. In computer terms, it is basically a n-dimensional array. A scalar (one value) is a tensor with 0 dimensions, a vector is a tensor with 1 dimension, a matrix is a tensor with 2 dimensions.</p>

<p>It's possible to define a tensor in Ruby using the <code>Array</code> class of Ruby but it gets tedious when defining multi-dimensional tensors. Also, the <code>Array</code> object is designed to be heterogeneous which means that the elements of the array can be of different type or different classes which would seem as a plus point overall but it has a huge downside. Due to <code>Array</code> being heterogeneous, the memory allocation has to be in such a way that any element of any size can be added or removed from the array, which causes a lot of re-allocations. Also, the indexing and other array functions gets slower due to the heterogeneous nature.</p>

<p>What if there's a scenario where there is only one type of tensor elements, which means that a homogeneous array would also do, and there are memory and speed constraints? <code>NumRuby</code> is the solution for such requirements.</p>

<h2>Tensors in NumRuby</h2>

<p>A tensor can be defined using the <code>NMatrix</code> object of <code>NumRuby</code>.</p>

<p><code>ruby
N = NMatrix.new [shape], [elements], :type
</code></p>

<p><code>shape</code> is the number of dimensions and size of each dimension of the tensor. For example, <code>[2, 2, 2]</code> shape tensor is a tensor with 3 dimensions and each dimension of size 2, hence number of elements is 8. A sample value of elements array for this could be <code>[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]</code>. <code>type</code> is the data type of each of the tensor element, it could be any of <code>:nm_bool</code>, <code>:nm_int</code>, <code>:nm_float32</code>, <code>:nm_float64</code>, <code>:nm_complex32</code> or <code>:nm_complex64</code> depending on the requirements.</p>

<p>An example usage is shown below:</p>

<p><code>ruby
[1] pry(main)&gt; N = NMatrix.new [2, 2], [1, 2, 3, 4], :nm_int
=&gt;
[
 [1, 2],
 [3, 4]
]
[2] pry(main)&gt; N.elements
=&gt; [1, 2, 3, 4]
[3] pry(main)&gt; N.shape
=&gt; [2, 2]
[4] pry(main)&gt; N[0, 0]
=&gt; 1
[5] pry(main)&gt; N[1, 0]
=&gt; 3
[6] pry(main)&gt; N.dtype
=&gt; :nm_int
</code></p>

<h2>Elementwise Operations</h2>

<p>One can also perform elementwise operations using <code>NumRuby</code>. Elementwise operations are broadly of 2 types, Uni-operand and bi-operand.</p>

<h3>Uni-Operand Operations</h3>

<p>Uni-operand operators are those that apply to just one tensor. For example, sine, cos or tan of each of element of the tensor.</p>

<p><code>ruby
[1] pry(main)&gt; N = NMatrix.new [2, 2], [1, 2, 3, 4], :nm_float64
=&gt;
[
 [1.0, 2.0],
 [3.0, 4.0]
]
[2] pry(main)&gt; N.sin
=&gt;
[
 [0.8414709848078965,  0.9092974268256817],
 [0.1411200080598672, -0.7568024953079282]
]
[3] pry(main)&gt; N.cos
=&gt;
[
 [ 0.5403023058681398, -0.4161468365471424],
 [-0.9899924966004454, -0.6536436208636119]
]
</code></p>

<h3>Bi-Operand Operations</h3>

<p>Bi-operand operators are those that apply to two tensor. For example, addition, subtraction or multiplication of each of the corresponding elements of the the 2 tensor.</p>

<p><code>ruby
[1] pry(main)&gt; N = NMatrix.new [2, 2], [1, 2, 3, 4], :nm_float64
=&gt;
[
 [1.0, 2.0],
 [3.0, 4.0]
]
[2] pry(main)&gt; M = NMatrix.new [2, 2], [2, 2, 3, 3], :nm_float64
=&gt;
[
 [2.0, 2.0],
 [3.0, 3.0]
]
[3] pry(main)&gt; N+M
=&gt;
[
 [3.0, 4.0],
 [6.0, 7.0]
]
[4] pry(main)&gt; N*M
=&gt;
[
 [2.0,  4.0],
 [9.0, 12.0]
]
</code></p>

<h2>Linear Algebra</h2>

<p><code>NumRuby</code> also supports linear algebra capabilities for 2-dimensional tensors. One can easily do operations such as matrix inverse, dot product, matrix decompositions.</p>

<p><code>ruby
[1] pry(main)&gt; N = NMatrix.new [2, 2], [1, 2, 3, 4], :nm_float64
=&gt;
[
 [1.0, 2.0],
 [3.0, 4.0]
]
[2] pry(main)&gt; M = NMatrix.new [2, 2], [2, 2, 3, 3], :nm_float64
=&gt;
[
 [2.0, 2.0],
 [3.0, 3.0]
]
[3] pry(main)&gt; N.dot(M)
=&gt;
[
 [ 8.0,  8.0],
 [18.0, 18.0]
]
[4] pry(main)&gt; N.invert
=&gt;
[
 [-1.9999999999999996,  0.9999999999999998],
 [ 1.4999999999999998, -0.4999999999999999]
]
[5] pry(main)&gt; N.det
=&gt; -2.0
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GSoC 2019: Adding features to NMatrix core]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2019/08/26/gsoc-2019-adding-features-to-nmatrix-core/"/>
    <updated>2019-08-26T23:49:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2019/08/26/gsoc-2019-adding-features-to-nmatrix-core</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The GSoC coding period has come to an end. It's been quite a learning experience for me and has given me an opportunity to come out of my comfort zone and explore new things. I feel quite delighted knowing that I have contributed a significant amount to the project. This post summarizes my work on <a href="https://github.com/sciruby/numruby">NumRuby</a> during the GSoC period.</p>

<p>GSoC 2019 proposal - <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1MR01QZeX_8h7a16nmkOYlyrVt--osB1Yg9Vo0xXYtSw/edit?usp=sharing">https://docs.google.com/document/d/1MR01QZeX_8h7a16nmkOYlyrVt--osB1Yg9Vo0xXYtSw/edit?usp=sharing</a></p>

<h2>Pull requests</h2>

<ul>
<li>Indexing, iterating, slicing - <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/19">https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/19</a></li>
<li>Fix compiler warnings - <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/21">https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/21</a></li>
<li>Dimensional iterators - <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/22">https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/22</a></li>
<li>Broadcasting - <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/23">https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/23</a></li>
<li>Lapack wrappers - <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/26">https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/26</a></li>
<li>NumRuby::Linalg - <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/30">https://github.com/SciRuby/numruby/pull/30</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Blog Posts</h2>

<ul>
<li>GSoC project introduction - <a href="https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/05/21/gsoc-project-introduction-nmatrix.html">https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/05/21/gsoc-project-introduction-nmatrix.html</a></li>
<li>GSoC weeks 1, 2 - <a href="https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/06/10/gsoc-week-1-2.html">https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/06/10/gsoc-week-1-2.html</a></li>
<li>GSoC weeks 3, 4 - <a href="https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/06/26/gsoc-week-3-4.html">https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/06/26/gsoc-week-3-4.html</a></li>
<li>GSoC weeks 5, 6 - <a href="https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/07/10/gsoc-week-5-6.html">https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/07/10/gsoc-week-5-6.html</a></li>
<li>GSoC weeks 7, 8 - <a href="https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/07/25/gsoc-week-7-8.html">https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/07/25/gsoc-week-7-8.html</a></li>
<li>GSoC weeks 9, 10 - <a href="https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/08/16/gsoc-week-9-10.html">https://uditgulati.github.io/blog/open-source/2019/08/16/gsoc-week-9-10.html</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Future work</h2>

<ul>
<li>As these features are core to NMatrix, they need to be tested more tightly and benchmarked. Also, since this is the first implementation of the features, some modifications can make these features more reliable and faster.</li>
<li>More iterators are to be implemented in order to have a richer NMatrix API.</li>
<li>The issue with slicing needs to be fixed soon. Also, need to standardize the formatting used for slice range specification.</li>
<li>Broadcasting needs to be tested and benchmarked. This will let us improve it's reliability and performance. A few APIs could be exposed which would let a user manually broadcast a matrix to a given shape.</li>
<li>NumRuby::Lapack needs to have proper exception handling for LAPACK routines. This will be done by reading the info value returned by routine and raising exception accordingly.</li>
<li>NumRuby::Linalg can be extended to have even more methods.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>I wanna thank Ruby Science Foundation, all mentors and org admins for providing me this wonderful opportunity to enhance my knowledge and work on a project. I would also like to thank Google for organizing such a wonderful program due to which I got introduced to Open-source and Ruby Science Foundation. I especially want to thank my mentor Prasun Anand for guiding me through this period, keeping me motivated and for tolerating my procrastination.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GSoC 2016: NMatrix and JRuby]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2016/10/24/gsoc-2016-port-nmatrix-to-jruby/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-24T22:43:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2016/10/24/gsoc-2016-port-nmatrix-to-jruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>I worked on "Port NMatrix to JRuby" in the context of the Google
Summer of Code (GSoC) 2016 and I am pleased to announce that NMatrix
can now be used in JRuby.</p>

<p>With JRuby NMatrix, a linear algebra library, wraps <a href="http://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-math/">Apache Commons Math</a> for its most
basic functionalities. NMatrix supports dense matrices containing
either doubles or Ruby objects as the data type. The performance of JRuby
with Apache Commons Maths is quite satisfactory (see below for performance
comparisons) even without making use of JRuby threading capabilities.</p>

<p>I have also ported the <a href="https://github.com/agisga/mixed_models">mixed_models gem</a>, which
uses NMatrix heavily at its core, to JRuby. This gem allowed us
to test NMatrix-JRuby with real-life data.</p>

<p>This blog post summarizes my work on the project with SciRuby, and
reports the final status of the project.</p>

<p>The original GSoC proposal, plan and application can be found <a href="https://github.com/prasunanand/resume/blob/master/gsoc2016_application.md">here</a>. Until merging
is complete, commits are available <a href="https://github.com/prasunanand/nmatrix/commits/jruby_port">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Performance</h2>

<p>I have benchmarked some of the NMatrix functionalities. The following
plots compare the performance between NMatrix-JRuby, NMatrix-MRI, and
NMatrix-MRI using LAPACK/ATLAS libraries. (Note: MRI refers to the
reference implementation of Ruby, for those who are new.)</p>

<p>Notes:</p>

<ol>
<li>LAPACK and ATLAS aren't involved in most element-wise operations, such as addition and subtraction.</li>
<li>NMatrix-MRI relies on LAPACK/ATLAS for calculating determinants and LU Decomposition (lud).</li>
</ol>


<p><img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/plots/add.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 3: Matrix Addition" alt="Alt Matrix Addition" />
<img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/plots/subt.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 4: Matrix Subtraction" alt="Alt Matrix Subtraction" />
<img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/plots/mult.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 5: Matrix Multiplication" alt="Alt Matrix Multiplication" />
<img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/plots/gamma.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 6: Gamma Operator" alt="Alt Gamma operator" />
<img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/plots/det.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 7: Determinant" alt="Alt Determinant" />
<img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/plots/lud.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 8: LU Facorization" alt="Alt LU Facorization" /></p>

<h3>Result</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>For two-dimensional matrices, NMatrix-JRuby is currently slower than NMatrix-MRI for matrix multiplication and matrix decomposition functionalities (calculating determinant and factoring a matrix). NMatrix-JRuby is faster than NMatrix-MRI for other functionalities of a two-dimensional matrix &mdash; like addition, subtraction, trigonometric operations, etc.</p></li>
<li><p>NMatrix-JRuby is a clear winner when we are working with matrices of arbitrary dimensions.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Implementation</h2>

<h3>Storing <em>n</em>-dimensional matrices as one-dimensional arrays</h3>

<p>The major components of an <code>NMatrix</code> are shape, elements, dtype and
stype. When initialized, the dense type stores the elements as a one-dimensional
array; in the JRuby port, the <code>ArrayRealVector</code> class is used to store
the elements.</p>

<p><code>@s</code> stores elements, <code>@shape</code> stores the shape of the matrix, while
<code>@dtype</code> and <code>@stype</code> store the data type and storage type
respectively. Currently, I have nmatrix-jruby implemented only for
<code>:float64</code> (double) and Ruby <code>:object</code> data types.</p>

<p>NMatrix-MRI uses <code>struct</code> as a <code>type</code> to store <code>dim</code>, <code>shape</code>, <code>offset</code>, <code>count</code>, <code>src</code>
of an NMatrix. <code>ALLOC</code> and <code>xfree</code> are used to wrap the NMatrix attributes to C structs
and release the unrequired memory.</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/nmatrix.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 1: NMatrix" alt="NMatrix" /></p>

<h3>Slicing and Rank</h3>

<p>Implementing slicing was the toughest part of NMatrix-JRuby
implementation. <code>NMatrix@s</code> stores the elements of a matrix as a
one-dimensional array. The elements along any dimension are accessed with the
help of the stride. <code>NMatrix#get_stride</code> calculates the stride with
the help of the dimension and shape and returns an Array.</p>

<p>```ruby
def get_stride(nmatrix)
  stride = Array.new()
  (0...nmatrix.dim).each do |i|</p>

<pre><code>stride[i] = 1;
(i+1...dim).each do |j|
  stride[i] *= nmatrix.shape[j]
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  stride
end
```</p>

<p><code>NMatrix#[]</code> and <code>NMatrix#[]=</code> are thus able to read and write the
elements of a matrix. NMatrix#MRI uses the <code>@s</code> object which stores
the stride when the nmatrix is initialized.</p>

<p><code>NMatrix#[]</code> calls the <code>#xslice</code> operator which calls <code>#get_slice</code>
operator that use the stride to determine whether we are accessing a
single element or multiple elements. If there are multiple elements,
<code>#dense_storage_get</code> returns an NMatrix object with the elements along
the dimension.</p>

<p>NMatrix-MRI differs from NMatrix-JRuby implementation as it makes sure
that memory is properly utilized as the memory needs to be properly
garbage collected.</p>

<p>```ruby
def xslice(args)
  result = nil</p>

<p>  if self.dim &lt; args.length</p>

<pre><code>raise(ArgumentError,"wrong number of arguments\
   (#{args} for #{effective_dim(self)})")
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>result = Array.new()
slice = get_slice(@dim, args, @shape)
stride = get_stride(self)
if slice[:single]
  if (@dtype == :object)
    result = @s[dense_storage_get(slice,stride)]
  else
    s = @s.toArray().to_a
    result = @s.getEntry(dense_storage_get(slice,stride))
  end
else
  result = dense_storage_get(slice,stride)
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  return result
end
```</p>

<p><code>NMatrix#[]=</code> calls the <code>#dense_storage_set</code> operator which calls
 <code>#get_slice</code> operator that use the stride to find out whether we are
 accessing a single element or multiple elements. If there are
 multiple elements <code>#set_slice</code> recursively sets the elements of the
 matrix then returns an NMatrix object with the elements along the
 dimension.</p>

<p>All the relevant code for slicing can be found <a href="https://github.com/prasunanand/nmatrix/blob/jruby_port/lib/nmatrix/jruby/slice.rb">here</a>.</p>

<h3>Enumerators</h3>

<p>NMatrix-MRI uses the C code for enumerating the elements of a
matrix. Just as with slicing, the NMatrix-JRuby uses pure Ruby code in
place of the C code. Currently, all the enumerators for dense matrices
with real data-type have been implemented and are properly
functional. Enumerators for objects have not yet been implemented.</p>

<p>```ruby
def each_with_indices
  nmatrix = create_dummy_nmatrix
  stride = get_stride(self)
  offset = 0
  #Create indices and initialize them to zero
  coords = Array.new(dim){ 0 }</p>

<p>  shape_copy =  Array.new(dim)
  (0...size).each do |k|</p>

<pre><code>dense_storage_coords(nmatrix, k, coords, stride, offset)
slice_index = dense_storage_pos(coords,stride)
ary = Array.new
if (@dtype == :object)
  ary &lt;&lt; self.s[slice_index]
else
  ary &lt;&lt; self.s.toArray.to_a[slice_index]
end
(0...dim).each do |p|
  ary &lt;&lt; coords[p]
end

# yield the array which now consists of the value and the indices
yield(ary)
</code></pre>

<p>  end if block_given?
  nmatrix.s = @s</p>

<p>  return nmatrix
 end
```</p>

<h3>Two-Dimensional Matrices</h3>

<p>Linear algebra is mostly about two-dimensional matrices. In NMatrix,
when performing calculations in a two-dimensional matrix, a one-dimensional array
is converted to a two-dimensional matrix. A two-dimensional matrix is
stored in the JRuby implementation as a <code>BlockRealMatrix</code> or
<code>Array2DRowRealMatrix</code>. Each has its own advantages.</p>

<h4>Getting a 2D Matrix</h4>

<p><img src="https://github.com/prasunanand/gsoc_blog/blob/master/img/sciruby_blog/matrixGenerate.png?raw=true" title="Fig. 2: Getting a 2D-matrix" alt="Alt Getting a 2D-matrix" /></p>

<p>```java
public class MatrixGenerator
{
  public static double[][] getMatrixDouble(double[] array, int row, int col)
  {</p>

<pre><code>double[][] matrix = new double[row][col];
for (int index=0, i=0; i &lt; row ; i++){
    for (int j=0; j &lt; col; j++){
        matrix[i][j]= array[index];
        index++;
    }
}
return matrix;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h4>Convert a 2D-matrix to 1D-array</h4>

<p>```java
public class ArrayGenerator
{
  public static double[] getArrayDouble(double[][] matrix, int row, int col)
  {</p>

<pre><code>double[] array = new double[row * col];
for (int index=0, i=0; i &lt; row ; i++){
    for (int j=0; j &lt; col; j++){
        array[index] = matrix[i][j];
        index++;
    }
}
return array;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h4>Why use a Java method instead of Ruby method?</h4>

<ol>
<li><p><em>Memory Usage and Garbage Collection:</em> A scientific library is memory intensive and hence, every step counts. The JRuby interpreter doesn't need to dynamically guess the data type and uses less memory, typically around one-tenth of it. If the memory is properly utilized, when the GC kicks in, the GC has to clear less used memory space.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Speed:</em> Using java method greatly improves the speed &mdash; by around 1000 times, when compared to using the Ruby method.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2><strong>Operators</strong></h2>

<p>All the operators from NMatrix-MRI have been implemented except
modulus. The binary operators were easily implemented through Commons
Math API and Java Math API.</p>

<p>```ruby
def +(other)
  result = create_dummy_nmatrix
  if (other.is_a?(NMatrix))</p>

<pre><code>#check dimension
raise(ShapeError, "Cannot add matrices with different dimension")\
if (@dim != other.dim)
#check shape
(0...dim).each do |i|
  raise(ShapeError, "Cannot add matrices with different shapes") \
  if (@shape[i] != other.shape[i])
end
result.s = @s.copy.add(other.s)
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>result.s = @s.copy.mapAddToSelf(other)
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  result
end
```</p>

<p>Unary Operators (Trigonometric, Exponentiation and Log operators) have been implemented using <code>#mapToSelf</code> method that takes a <a href="https://commons.apache.org/proper/commons-math/javadocs/api-3.6.1/org/apache/commons/math3/analysis/UnivariateFunction.html"><code>Univariate function</code></a> as an argument. <code>#mapToSelf</code> maps every element of ArrayRealVector object to the <code>Univariate function</code>, that is passed to it and returns <code>self</code> object.</p>

<p><code>ruby
def sin
  result = create_dummy_nmatrix
  result.s = @s.copy.mapToSelf(Sin.new())
  result
end
</code></p>

<p>NMatrix#method(arg) has been implemented using bivariate functions
provided by Commons Math API and Java Math API.</p>

<p><code>ruby
def gamma
  result = create_dummy_nmatrix
  result.s = ArrayRealVector.new MathHelper.gamma(@s.toArray)
  result
end
</code></p>

<p>```java
import org.apache.commons.math3.special.Gamma;</p>

<p>public class MathHelper{
  ...
  public static double[] gamma(double[] arr){</p>

<pre><code>double[] result = new double[arr.length];
for(int i = 0; i&lt; arr.length; i++){
  result[i] = Gamma.gamma(arr[i]);
}
return result;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  ...
}
```</p>

<h3>Decomposition</h3>

<p>NMatrix-MRI relies on LAPACK and ATLAS for matrix decomposition and
solving functionalities. Apache Commons Math provides a different set
of API for decomposing a matrix and solving an equation. For example,
<code>#potrf</code> and other LAPACK specific functions have not been implemented
as they are not required at all.</p>

<p>Calculating determinant in NMatrix is tricky where a matrix is reduced
either to a lower or upper matrix and the diagonal elements of the
matrix are multiplied to get the result. Also, the correct sign of the
result (whether positive or negative) is taken into account while
calculating the determinant. However, NMatrix-JRuby uses Commons Math
API to calculate the determinant.</p>

<p>```ruby
def det_exact
  if (@dim != 2 || @shape[0] != @shape[1])</p>

<pre><code>raise(ShapeError, "matrices must be square to have a determinant defined")
return nil
</code></pre>

<p>  end
  to_return = LUDecomposition.new(self.twoDMat).getDeterminant()
end
```</p>

<p>Given below is code that shows how Cholesky decomposition has been
implemented by using Commons Math API.</p>

<h4>Cholesky Decomposition</h4>

<p>```ruby
  def factorize_cholesky</p>

<pre><code>cholesky = CholeskyDecomposition.new(self.twoDMat)
l = create_dummy_nmatrix
twoDMat = cholesky.getL
l.s = ArrayRealVector.new(ArrayGenerator.getArrayDouble\
    (twoDMat.getData, @shape[0], @shape[1]))

u = create_dummy_nmatrix
twoDMat = cholesky.getLT
u.s = ArrayRealVector.new(ArrayGenerator.getArrayDouble\
  (twoDMat.getData, @shape[0], @shape[1]))
return [u,l]
</code></pre>

<p>  end
```
Similarly, LU Decomposition and QR factorization have been implemented.</p>

<h4>LU Decomposition</h4>

<p><a href="https://github.com/prasunanand/nmatrix/blob/jruby_port/lib/nmatrix/jruby/math.rb#L365">Code</a></p>

<h4>QR Factorization</h4>

<p><a href="https://github.com/prasunanand/nmatrix/blob/jruby_port/lib/nmatrix/jruby/math.rb#L392">Code</a></p>

<h4><code>NMatrix#solve</code></h4>

<p>The solve method currently uses LU and Cholesky decomposition.</p>

<p>```ruby
  def solve(b, opts = {})</p>

<pre><code>raise(ShapeError, "Must be called on square matrix")\
   unless self.dim == 2 &amp;&amp; self.shape[0] == self.shape[1]
raise(ShapeError, "number of rows of b must equal number\
   of cols of self") if self.shape[1] != b.shape[0]
raise(ArgumentError, "only works with dense matrices") if self.stype != :dense
raise(ArgumentError, "only works for non-integer, non-object dtypes")\
   if integer_dtype? or object_dtype? or b.integer_dtype? or b.object_dtype?

opts = { form: :general }.merge(opts)
x    = b.clone
n    = self.shape[0]
nrhs = b.shape[1]

nmatrix = create_dummy_nmatrix
case opts[:form]
when :general, :upper_tri, :upper_triangular, :lower_tri, :lower_triangular
  #LU solver
  solver = LUDecomposition.new(self.twoDMat).getSolver
  nmatrix.s = solver.solve(b.s)
  return nmatrix
when :pos_def, :positive_definite
  solver = Choleskyecomposition.new(self.twoDMat).getSolver
  nmatrix.s = solver.solve(b.s)
  return nmatrix
else
  raise(ArgumentError, "#{opts[:form]} is not a valid form option")
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
```</p>

<h4><code>NMatrix#matrix_solve</code></h4>

<p>Suppose we need to solve a system of linear equations:</p>

<pre><code>                    AX = B
</code></pre>

<p>where A is an m×n matrix, B and X are n×p matrices, we need to solve this equation by iterating through B.</p>

<p>NMatrix-MRI implements this functionality using <code>NMatrix::BLAS::cblas_trsm</code> method. However, for NMatrix-JRuby,  <code>NMatrix#matrix_solve</code> is the analogous method used.</p>

<p>```ruby
  def matrix_solve rhs</p>

<pre><code>if rhs.shape[1] &gt; 1
  nmatrix = NMatrix.new :copy
  nmatrix.shape = rhs.shape
  res = []
  #Solve a matrix and store the vectors in a matrix
  (0...rhs.shape[1]).each do |i|
    res &lt;&lt; self.solve(rhs.col(i)).s.toArray.to_a
  end
  #res is in col major format
  result = ArrayGenerator.getArrayColMajorDouble \
     res.to_java :double, rhs.shape[0], rhs.shape[1]
  nmatrix.s = ArrayRealVector.new result

  return nmatrix
else
  return self.solve rhs
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
```</p>

<p>Currently, Hessenberg transformation for NMatrix-JRuby has not been implemented.</p>

<h3>Other dtypes</h3>

<p>I have tried implementing float dtypes using <code>FloatMatrix</code> class
provide by jblas.  jblas was used instead of Commons Math as the
latter uses <code>Field Elements</code> for Floats and it had some issues
with <code>Reflection</code> and <code>Type Erasure</code>.
However, using jblas resulted in errors due to precision.</p>

<h2>Code Organisation and Deployment</h2>

<p>To minimise conflict with the MRI codebase all the JRuby front end
code has been placed in the <code>/lib/nmatrix/jruby</code>
directory. <code>lib/nmatrix/nmatrix.rb</code> decides whether to load
<code>nmatrix.so</code> or <code>nmatrix_jruby.rb</code> after detecting the Ruby platform.</p>

<p>The added advantage is that the Ruby interpreter must not decide which
function to call at run-time. The impact on performance can be seen
when programs which intensively use NMatrix for linear algebraic
computations (<em>e.g.</em>, mixed_models) are run.</p>

<h2>Spec Report</h2>

<p>After the port; this is the final report that summarizes the number of tests that successfully pass:</p>

<h3>NMatrix</h3>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>Spec file</th>
<th align="center">Total Tests</th>
<th align="center">Success</th>
<th align="center">Failure</th>
<th align="center">Pending</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>00_nmatrix_spec</td>
<td align="center">188</td>
<td align="center">139</td>
<td align="center">43</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>01_enum_spec</td>
<td align="center">17</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">09</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>02_slice_spec</td>
<td align="center">144</td>
<td align="center">116</td>
<td align="center">28</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>03_nmatrix_monkeys_spec</td>
<td align="center">12</td>
<td align="center">11</td>
<td align="center">01</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>elementwise_spec</td>
<td align="center">38</td>
<td align="center">21</td>
<td align="center">17</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>homogeneous_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">07</td>
<td align="center">06</td>
<td align="center">01</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>math_spec</td>
<td align="center">737</td>
<td align="center">541</td>
<td align="center">196</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>shortcuts_spec</td>
<td align="center">81</td>
<td align="center">57</td>
<td align="center">24</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>stat_spec</td>
<td align="center">72</td>
<td align="center">40</td>
<td align="center">32</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>slice_set_spec</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">04</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<br>


<h4>Why do some tests fail?</h4>

<ol>
<li>Complex dtype has not been implemented.</li>
<li>Sparse matrices (list and yale) have not been implemented.</li>
<li>Decomposition methods that are specific to LAPACK and ATLAS have not been implemented.</li>
<li>Integer dtype is not properly assigned to <code>floor</code>, <code>ceil</code>, and <code>round</code> methods.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Mixed_Models</h3>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>Spec file</th>
<th align="center">Total Test</th>
<th align="center">Success</th>
<th align="center">Failure</th>
<th align="center">Pending</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>Deviance_spec</td>
<td align="center">04</td>
<td align="center">04</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>LMM_spec</td>
<td align="center">195</td>
<td align="center">195</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>LMM_categorical_data_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">48</td>
<td align="center">45</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>LMMFormula_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">05</td>
<td align="center">05</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>LMM_interaction_effects_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">82</td>
<td align="center">82</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>LMM_nested_effects_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">40</td>
<td align="center">40</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>matrix_methods_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">52</td>
<td align="center">52</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>ModelSpecification_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">07</td>
<td align="center">07</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>NelderMeadWithConstraints_spec.rb</td>
<td align="center">08</td>
<td align="center">08</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
<td align="center">0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Future Work</h2>

<p>NMatrix on JRuby offers comparable speeds to MRI. For specific
computations it will be possible to leverage the threading support of
JRuby and speed up things using multiple cores.</p>

<p>Adding new functionality to NMatrix-JRuby will be easy from
here. Personally, I am interested to add OpenCL support to leverage
the GPU computational capacity available on most machines today.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The main goal of this project was to to gain from the performance JRuby offers,
and bring a unified interface for linear algebra between MRI and JRuby.</p>

<p>By the end of GSoC, I have been able to successfully create a linear
algebra library, NMatrix for JRuby users, which they can easily run on
their machines &mdash; unless they want to use complex numbers, at
least for now.</p>

<p>I have mixed_models gem simultaneously ported to JRuby. Even here,
NMatrix-JRuby is very close to NMatrix-MRI, considering the performance .</p>

<h2>Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>I would like to express my sincere gratitude to my mentor Pjotr Prins
for the continuous support through the summers, and for his patience,
motivation, enthusiasm, and immense knowledge. I could not have
imagined having a better advisor and mentor, for this project.</p>

<p>I am very grateful to Google and the Ruby Science Foundation for this
golden opportunity.</p>

<p>I am very thankful to Charles Nutter, John Woods, Sameer Deshmukh,
Kenta Murata and Alexej Gossmann, who mentored me through the
project. It has been a great learning experience.</p>

<p>I thank my fellow GSoC participants Rajith, Lokesh and Gaurav who
helped me with certain aspects of my project.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[GSoC 2015: New NMatrix gems for advanced linear algebra features]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2015/08/19/gsoc-2015-nmatrix/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T09:57:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2015/08/19/gsoc-2015-nmatrix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My Google Summer of Code project was working on the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix">NMatrix project</a>, moving
functionality that depends on external libraries from the core <code>nmatrix</code>
gem to optional plugin gems. NMatrix is a Ruby library for linear algebra,
used by many other projects.
In addition to the code that was part of
NMatrix proper, NMatrix previously required the <a href="http://math-atlas.sourceforge.net/">ATLAS library</a>, which
implemented fast versions of common matrix operations like multiplication
and inversion, as well as more advanced operations like eigenvalue
decomposition and Cholesky decomposition.</p>

<p>There were two separate but related motivations for my project. The
first was to simplify the NMatrix installation
process. ATLAS can be difficult to install, so the installation
process for NMatrix was complicated, especially on
OS X, and may have discouraged people from using NMatrix.
The second motivation was that by separating out the ATLAS code from the
main NMatrix code, it would be easier to add new linear algebra backends
which provide similar features. Indeed, I implemented a second backend this
summer.</p>

<p>The end result of my summer's work:</p>

<ul>
<li>The core <code>nmatrix</code> gem does not depend on any external linear matrix
libraries. It provides non-optimized implementations of common matrix
operations.</li>
<li>All code that requires ATLAS has been moved into the new <code>nmatrix-atlas</code>
gem, so that
those who are only interested in the core functionality are not required to
install ATLAS. <code>nmatrix-atlas</code> provides optimized implementations of common matrix
operations, as well as advanced functions not available in <code>nmatrix</code>.
I wrote a blog post describing the setup for <a href="http://wlevine.github.io/2015/06/15/releasing-multiple-gems-with-c-extensions-from-the-same-repository.html">releasing multiple gems from the same repository</a>, which this required.</li>
<li>A new gem <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code>, which provides the same features as
<code>nmatrix-atlas</code>, but instead of depending specifically on the ATLAS
library, requires any generic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LAPACK">LAPACK</a> and
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Linear_Algebra_Subprograms">BLAS</a>
implementation. This should be easier to use for many users as they may
already have LAPACK installed (it comes pre-installed with OS X and is
commonly used in Linux systems), but not ATLAS.</li>
<li>The installation procedure is simplified, especially for those installing
just the <code>nmatrix</code> gem. Compare the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/wiki/Installation">new installation instructions</a>
to the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/wiki/Installation/2ac41c62d35c79468d3d8169be0ccba238c3c921">old ones</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>The one deviation from my original proposal was that I originally intended to remove
all the ATLAS code and release only the <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> plugin, so that we
would only have one interface to the advanced linear algebra functions, but I
decided to keep the ATLAS code, since the <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> code is new and
has not had a chance to be thoroughly tested.</p>

<h3>Usage</h3>

<p>```ruby
require 'nmatrix'</p>

<h1>create a 3-by-3 matrix</h1>

<p>a = NMatrix.new([3,3], [1,2,3, 4,5,6, 7,8,9], dtype: :float64)</p>

<h1>invert it using non-optimized NMatrix-internal implementation</h1>

<p>a.invert!
```</p>

<p>```ruby
require 'nmatrix'
require 'nmatrix/atlas' #or require 'nmatrix/lapacke'</p>

<h1>create a 3-by-3 matrix</h1>

<p>a = NMatrix.new([3,3], [1,2,3, 4,5,6, 7,8,9], dtype: :float64)</p>

<h1>invert it using optimized implementation provided by ATLAS</h1>

<p>a.invert!
```</p>

<p>For advanced functions not provided by the core <code>nmatrix</code> gem, for example
<a href="http://sciruby.com/nmatrix/docs/NMatrix.html#method-i-gesvd"><code>gesvd</code></a>, <code>nmatrix-atlas</code> and <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code>
provide a common interface:</p>

<p><code>ruby
require 'nmatrix'
require 'nmatrix/atlas'
a = NMatrix.new([4,5],[1,0,0,0,2, 0,0,3,0,0, 0,0,0,0,0, 0,4,0,0,0],
dtype: dtype)
u, s, vt = a.gesvd
</code></p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>Identical to the above, except for the require</h1>

<p>require 'nmatrix'
require 'nmatrix/lapacke'
a = NMatrix.new([4,5],[1,0,0,0,2, 0,0,3,0,0, 0,0,0,0,0, 0,4,0,0,0],
dtype: dtype)
u, s, vt = a.gesvd
```</p>

<p>If the developer wants to use an advanced feature, but does not care
whether the user is using <code>nmatrix-atlas</code>
or <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code>, they can <code>require nmatrix/lapack_plugin</code>, which will
require whichever of the two is available, instead of being forced to
choose between the two.</p>

<p>As a fun test of the new gems, I did a very simple benchmark, just
testing how long it took to invert a
1500-by-1500 matrix in place using <code>NMatix#invert!</code>:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>nmatrix</code> (no external libraries): 3.67s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-atlas</code>: 0.96s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> with ATLAS: 0.99s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> with OpenBLAS (multithreading enabled): 0.39s</li>
<li><code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> with reference implementations of LAPACK and BLAS: 3.72s</li>
</ul>


<p>This is not supposed to be a thorough or realistic benchmark (performance will
depend on your system, on how you built the libraries, and on the exact
functions that you use), but there
are still a few interesting conclusions we can draw from it:</p>

<ul>
<li>Performance is much better using the two highly optimized libraries
(ATLAS and OpenBLAS) than using either the NMatrix
internal implementation or the reference implementation.</li>
<li>When using ATLAS, performance is similar whether using <code>nmatrix-atlas</code>
and <code>nmatrix-lapacke</code> (this means we could consider deprecating
the <code>nmatix-atlas</code> gem).</li>
</ul>


<p>Overall, my summer has been productive. I implemented everything that I
proposed and feedback from testers so far has been positive.
I plan to stay involved with NMatrix, especially to follow up on any issues
related to my changes.
Although I won't be a student next summer, I would certainly consider
participating in Google Summer of Code in the future as a mentor.
I'd like to
thank my mentor John Woods and the rest of the SciRuby community for support
and feedback throughout the summer.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NMatrix's first beta release (belated announcement)]]></title>
    <link href="http://sciruby.com/blog/2015/02/14/nmatrix-beta-released-belated-announcement/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-14T14:56:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://sciruby.com/blog/2015/02/14/nmatrix-beta-released-belated-announcement</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Almost two months ago, in December, we <a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/nmatrix">release our first beta of NMatrix</a>, our
linear algebra library for the Ruby language.</p>

<p>Rather than discussing what NMatrix has (which you can find in the <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/nmatrix/blob/master/README.rdoc">readme</a>),
I want to take this opportunity to discuss where we'd like it to go in the future. Think of this as our roadmap to 1.0.</p>

<h2>External Library Requirements</h2>

<p>NMatrix currently has an extremely limited set of Ruby gem dependencies &mdash; essentially only packable, which is
needed for some of the I/O functionality &mdash; but as with other linear algebra libraries, its native library
requirements can be problematic.</p>

<p>Specifically, NMatrix requires ATLAS &mdash; which is virtually impossible to install on many Macs, and is no longer
readily available with Yosemite &mdash; and also likes to have LAPACK around. Moreover, some would prefer to use other
math libraries with NMatrix.</p>

<p>There are several partial solutions. The clearest is that any components of NMatrix which require external non-standard
libraries need to be abstracted into separate gems &mdash; such as <tt>nmatrix-atlas</tt> and <tt>nmatrix-io</tt> &mdash; and
that these components should be interchangeable with others. NMatrix then needs to be able to fall back on either native
C/C++ or Ruby implementations of certain functionalities.</p>

<p>To this end, a number of simple LAPACK and CBLAS functions have been implemented in NMatrix, with volunteers working on
a few others (the list is available in the README). <a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/sciruby/wiki/Google-Summer-of-Code-2015-Ideas#abstraction-of-atlascblasclapack-or-openblas-into-a-separate-gem">One of our proposed Google Summer of Code 2015 project ideas</a> involves
breaking up NMatrix into several gems.</p>

<p>The end result will be a much simpler installation process, and more freedom of choice.</p>

<h2>Removal of Unnecessary Features</h2>

<p>We thought it would be quite clever to include rational number support in NMatrix, including three types (32-bit, 64-bit,
and 128-bit). Unfortunately, these types increase compilation time by about 30% (back-of-the-envelope calculation), and
aren't particularly useful since most matrix operations with rationals as inputs give irrational-valued matrices
as their outputs. The inclusion of rational types also complicates the codebase.</p>

<p>Additionally, rationals are computationally problematic; what happens if there is overflow? Ruby handles overflow gracefully
in its own rational type, which NMatrix users would still be able to utilize via the <tt>:object</tt> dtype.</p>

<h2>You</h2>

<p>The biggest change going forward is that NMatrix development needs to support actual use-cases. In the past, we've aimed
to flesh out support for sparse storage formats, as well as math operations for the dense storage-type. It is folly to
develop features no one wants to use. Future core development, then, will aim to make NMatrix's current feature set more
usable.</p>

<p>That means that future non-core development depends on you. What would you like to see in NMatrix? What would make it
more useful for you?</p>

<p>If you want to become involved, now is a good time. We're getting ready to submit a Google Summer of Code application
(our third, I believe), and we're in need of students &mdash; <em>and especially mentors</em>. Please consider joining
our <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/sciruby-dev">mailing list</a> and adding yourself as a mentor on the
<a href="https://github.com/SciRuby/sciruby/wiki/Google-Summer-of-Code-2015-Ideas">ideas page</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks so much for your support!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
